This is our
planet's hothouse
the jungle
the tropical rainforest
Forests like
these occupy only 3% of the land
yet they're home
to over half of the world's species
But how do so many different kinds of plants and animals
find the space
here to live alongside one another？
On the dark
humid forest floor
the jungle
appears to be lifeless
Often the only
signs of life are what you hear
A male bluebird
of paradise is advertising for a mate
It's quite a
performance
But he's not the
only bird of paradise here
Keen to make
an impression
There are nearly
40 different kinds on the island of New Guinea
Each with a display seemingly more bizarre than the rest
A rifle bird
of paradise
Like many
jungle animals
birds of paradise avoid competing with each other
And these do so by living in different parts of this junglecovered island
The sixprumed
bird of paradise
displays in his
special clearing on the forest floor
The magnificent bird of paradise favours the low branches of bushes
Its female is
modestly dressed
The male has a
good set of lungs
But he'll have to
do more than flutter his eyelids
If he wants
to impress her
It'll all depend
on his performance
The females may
be dull looking
But they're
very picky
And it's time for
a really close inspection
His right
side looks fine
but what
about his left？
Pretty impressive
but is he
magnificent enough？
Oh dear
her departure says it all
Generations of
choosy females
Have driven the
evolution of these remarkable displays
The more
extravagant a male is
The more likely
he will be noticed
New Guinea lies
in a warm tropical belt
that girdles our
planet around the equator
With abundant
rainfall and 12 hours of daylight
365 days a year
It's here that
rainforests flourish
Surprisingly
only 2% of the
sunlight filters down to the forest floor
Down here
seedlings
struggle to grow
But the gloom
is not eternal
The death of a
forest giant is always saddening
But it has
to happen
if the forest is
to remain healthy
The sudden
blaze of sunlight
will bring life
to the forest floor
A single
hectare of rainforest
may contain as
many as 250 species of tree
That's nearly ten
times the number that grow in Britain
And the thirst
for light triggers a race
for a
place in the sun
There's no
time to waste
A seed that may
have fallen only a few days ago
now burst
through the leaf litter
With so many
competitors
getting a good
start is critical
But each plant
has its own particular strategy
For making the
most of this rare opportunity
The seeds of
hardwoods are quick to germinate
But like the
fabled tortoise
their strategy is
to be slow and steady
Vines and
other climbers
Put all their
energy into rapid vertical growth
rather than girth
Though they'll
need to be well supported
The climbers'
strategy looks chaotic
But there's
method in their madness
Their growing
tips circle like lassoes
Searching out
anchors for their spindly stems
They put coils
in their tendrils
so that if
their support moves
they will
stretch and not snap
But the front
runners at this stage
the first to
fill the clearing
are pioneers
like the macaranga's
Their immense
leaves capture huge amounts of sunlight
so fueling
their growth
As a result
the macaranga
grow a remarkable eight metres a year
surging ahead of
almost all their rivals
In the race
for the top spot
Hundreds
will start
Yet few will ever
reach the finishing line
Their growth cut
short by the diminishing light
In less
than four years
The gap
will have gone
But that's not
the end of the race
The ultimate
winners are the tortoises
the slow and
steady hardwoods
When the shortlived pioneers have fallen
it's the hardwoods that take their place
And a 50 metre
giant like this one
may keep its
place in the sun
for another 200 years
At the top
is the canopy
the engine
room of the jungle
It's up here that
most of the animal life in the rainforest
can be found
But despite the
apparent abundance of vegetable food
gathering it
is seldom easy
With no
real seasons
each tree flowers
or fruits at a different time of the year
which means that
food is very widely spaced
Monkeys like
these tamarins
must search the
canopy for all kinds of food
if they're
to survive
But across the
world's rainforests
there's one type
of fruiting tree
that always delivers
The fig
Wherever they grow
figs are a magnet
for a great
diversity of animals
In the Amazon
the first
to appear
are the
spider monkeys
These
large primates
are big fig eaters
But they won't
have the tree to themselves for long
Others will
want to share
Like the diminutive emperor tamarins
The tamarins
love figs too
But being petite
means they're easily scared off
Squirrel
monkeys are also small
But they have
strength in numbers
Their timeshare
on the tree may be short
so their tactics
are more smash and grab
Capuchin monkeys
are the bully boys in these forests
And they want the
ripe figs for themselves
Figs are one of
the few trees that fruit the year round
So when other
food is scarce
these fruits are
always available somewhere or other
Even for leaf
eaters like howler monkeys
the ripe figs are
just too good to miss
And howlers are
too big for the capuchins to chase off
Figs are
so popular
that as many as
44 different kinds of bird and monkey
Have been seen
working a shift system
on a single tree
Because fruiting
trees are so valuable
many monkeys
are territorial
And if you live
in the treetops
There's perhaps no better way of staking your claim to a territory
Than this
The calls of the
siamang gibbons begin as a duet
between the
dominant male and female
The rest of their
family soon join in
and it results in
a frenzy of activity
The calls can
carry over a mile
and their
message is clear
They tell any
neighbouring siamangs
「This is
our territory
keep out」
Up here
the calls of
siamang gibbons
seem to
dominate the airwaves
But with the
jungle's incredible diversity
There are countless others trying to be heard too
Every layer seems
to beat to a different tune
In the
early morning
the forest's
chorus is particularly rich
Sounds travel
further in the cooler air
But few calls can
penetrate as far
through the dense
vegetation as this one
The deep bass
solo of a male orangutan
In the
middle of the day
little stirs
in the jungle
And the hot
dense air
muffled the sound
As the
afternoon wears on
a different set
of players begin to warm up
Insects
work in harmony
timing their calls to fall between the notes of others
Many singers
stick to precise schedules
And right on cue
the six o'
clock cicada
Night brings out
a whole new orchestra
The cacophony of
competing calls seems deafening to us
But frogs' ears are tuned to hear only the calls of their own kind
Songs of courtship echo from all around
Male gliding leaf
frogs leap from the treetops
To slow
their descent
they use their
huge webbed feet
as parachutes
These large
tree frogs
spend most of
their lives in the high canopy
And only come
down when it's time to breed
Once settled
they begin to
serenade their unseen females
Now
it's time for the
females to make their move
There's no
shortage of suitors
But this female
has already made her choice
She's heading
towards the loudest call
Because loud
calls come from big frogs
And big is best
But to reach him
she must run the
gauntlet of a gang of smaller suitors
Their only
chance of mating
is to make a
sneaky interception
He scored
But with more
females arriving all the time
It's not over
until the fat frog stops singing
Feet
so vital
for gliding
are now put
to other uses
Two's company
three's
inconvenient
But in any case
all male frogs
are equipped with dry thumbs
which enable them
to get a viselike grip
on their
moist partners
It's a case
of first come
first served
Living in such a
humid environment
means jungle frogs are less tied to puddles and pools
And these even
lay their eggs out of water
There's little
chance of them drying out
And up here
they're safer
from predators
Surprisingly
it doesn't rain
every day in the rainforest
But more still
falls here than anywhere else on Earth
On average
over two
metres a year
A single tree can
suck up hundreds of tons of water each year
But the trees can'
t use all this water
So much of it
returns to the air as vapour
forming
mist and clouds
In the Amazon
the largest unbroken stretch of rainforest in the world
Half of all the
rainwater that falls
comes from clouds
produced by the trees themselves
With so much rain
It's not surprising that many of the world's largest rivers are found in rainforests
Inside the forest
the high humidity
creates the
perfect conditions
for a
strange world
where life is
built on decay
Amoebalike slime
moulds cruise the surface
feeding on
bacteria and rotting vegetation
Fungi also
flourish on decay
These are the
fruiting bodies of the fungi
The only
visible sign
Of a vast
underground network
Of fungal
filaments
In temperate forests
the buildup of
leaf litter creates rich stores of nutrients
That however
doesn't happen here
Nutrients that
reach the soil are leached out by the rain
But fungi are connected to tree roots by their underground filaments
And by quickly
consuming the dead
they help to
recycle crucial minerals
Straight back
into the trees
And this recycling happens faster here
than anywhere
else on the planet
There are thought to be nearly a million different types of fungi in the tropics
The vast majority
still unknown to science
But one thing'
s for certain
Without fungi
rainforests
could not exist
Nothing goes to
waste in a rainforest
The fungi become
food for others
like these
beetle larvae
Finding the fungus isn't a problem for the grubs
Since their caring parents actually show them the way
Incredibly
80% of all
insects live in jungles
Few are more
successful than the ants
There can be 8
million individuals in a single hectare
But jungle ants
don't have it all their own way
These bullet ants
are showing some worrying symptoms
Spores from a
parasitic fungus called Cordyceps
Have infiltrated
their bodies and their minds
Its infected
brain directs this ant upwards
Then utterly
disorientated
it grips the
stem with its mandibles
Those afflicted
that are
discovered by the workers
are quickly
taken away and dumped
far away
from the colony
It seems extreme
but this is
the reason why
Like something
out of science fiction
the fruiting body
of the cordyceps erupts from the ant's head
It can take
three weeks to grow
And when finished
the deadly spores
will burst from its tip
Then
any ant in the
vicinity will be in serious risk of death
The fungus
is so virulent
it can wipe out
whole colonies of ants
And it's not just
ants that fall victim to this killer
There are literally thousands of different types of cordyceps fungi
and remarkably
each specialises
on just one species
But these attacks
do have a positive effect on the jungle's diversity
since
parasites like these
stop any one
group of animal getting the upper hand
The more numerous
a species becomes
the more likely
it will be attacked by its nemesis
a cordyceps fungus
With so much
competition
jungles have
become the home of the specialist
And this animal
in the
island of Borneo
is one of the
most unusual
It's a colugo
or flying lemur
though this is
something of a misnomer
As it doesn't
actually fly
and it certainly isn't a lemur
In fact
nobody's quite
sure who its closest relative is
The collugo
depends on a diet of young leaves
And to find
enough of them
it must move
from tree to tree
The leaves are
not very nutritious
But then getting
around doesn't use much energy
In a single night
a Kolugo might
have to travel as far as two miles
But that task
is made easier
by its superior
gliding skills
The secret of success in the competitive jungle is specialising
and this has led to the evolution of some very intimate relationships
between
plants and animals
These are
pitcher plants
also from Borneo
Adapted to living
in very low nutrient soils
the pitcher plant
gets most of its nourishment from insects
lured to
nectar glands
on the underside of the lids
Once on board
the waxy sides
of the pitcher
ensure little
chance of escape
Most slip to
a watery grave
At the bottom of
the pitcher glands secrete enzymes
which help to
digest the corpses
so feeding
the plant
But not all visitors have a fatal attraction to the pitchers
The red crab spider spends its entire life in the pitchers
hanging on with
threads of silk
Instead of
building a web
it relies on the
waterfilled pitcher to trap its food
When an
ant falls in
the spider
simply waits for it to drown
and then abseils
down for a spot of fishing
Alive
this ant would be
far too dangerous for the spider to tackle
So using the
pitchers as traps
means it can
get bigger meals
And the spider
doesn't rob the pitcher of everything
The digested remains of its booty will end up in the water
providing instant
food for the plant
Other food like
mosquito larvae
seems to be
out of reach
But the spider
has another surprising trick
By taking its own
air supply trapped in a bubble
The crab spider can actually dive to the very bottom of the pitcher
Once the
prey is captured
the spider hauls
itself back up its silken safety line
The pitcher is a
onestop shop for this spider
But it's not alone
In the jungle
there's competition for everything
Even a small
waterfilled pitcher plant
Such specialists
create the jungle's remarkable diversity
But finding
enough food to survive
is so challenging
that most animals
living here tend to be small
Though there
are exceptions
This is the Congo
in Africa
It's a vast
wilderness
and the least
explored of all jungles
From up here
the forest looks similar to the ones that grow in the Amazon or Southeast Asia
But down below
there are some
unexpected sights
Crisscrossing this forest
are countless
miles of highways
And they were
made by something big
Forest elephants
roam great distances in their search for food
But to survive
they must emerge
from the gloom of the forest
And clearings
like this one
are a magnet for
elephants from far and wide
These elephants
live in much smaller groups
than their
savannah cousins
This might be
the first time
that one group
will have seen another
for a month
For the
adult males
it's a
welcome break
in an otherwise
largely solitary existence
And they're not
the only animals attracted to the clearing
Forest buffaloes
and Red River hogs
are also
regular visitors
As are bongos
which are very
difficult to see outside these clearings
All these large
forest animals
have come here to
collect an essential element of their diet
that lies buried
beneath the mud
And the
elephant's trunk
is the perfect
tool for reaching it
To get
what they seek
the prospecting
elephants must first blow away
the covering
layer of silt
Satisfaction at last
They're collecting a particular kind of clay
that contains
vital minerals scarce in their natural diet
It may be mud
but there's just
nothing quite like it for enriching the blood
The clay also
helps to absorb the toxins
found in many
leaves that the elephants eat
There are other
benefits to coming here
These clearings
are the only places
where the forest
elephants can get together
in such numbers
When they
return to the forest
they will have to
go their separate ways once more
If large animals
are rare in jungles
then groups of
large animals actually living together
are even rarer
This posse
of hunters
is not
only formidable
it's also
very large
In their
search for food
chimpanzees move effortlessly between the forest floor and the canopy
They're one of
the few jungle animals able to do so
Figs are a vital
part of a chimpanzee's diet
And some just can'
t seem to get enough of them
But there's something special about this stretch of forest in Uganda
Fruit is
actually abundant
And a lot of food
supports lots of chimps
At 150 strong
this community of chimps
is the biggest
yet found in Africa
Their numbers
are so large
that they need
a big territory
lots of fig trees
and they're
willing to fight for it
These calls
announce the start of a raid
into land
controlled by their neighbours
As they leave
their core zone
the patrol
goes silent
occasionally
stopping to listen
Signs of the enemy
are detected
and examined closely
The chimp militia
are now at the
very edge of their territory
All need to be
on maximum alert
They must wait
and listen
An unfamiliar
chimp call raises the tension
It's an
uncertain time
The size of the
rival group is as yet unknown
Not far away
their neighbours
are feeding in a fig tree
oblivious to the
approaching dangers
The patrol
moves off
with a
sense of purpose
They must remain
silent until they close in on their rivals
The attack is on
To intimidate
their opponents
the aggressors
scream and drum on buttress roots
Several males
corner an enemy female
It's a
ferocious attack
and she's lucky
to escape with her life
Others are
not so fortunate
The battle won
a grisly
scene unfolds
An enemy youngster has been caught and killed
The carcass is
shared between members of the group
and eaten
Killing a competitor makes sense if you want to protect your food supply
But exactly why they cannibalise the dead chimp is not fully understood
It may simply be
a chance for some extra protein
Teamwork has brought this group of chimps great success
But they'll soon
reach the limits of their power
The competition for resources
ensures that no
one species dominates the jungle
The rainforest's
great diversity has come at a cost
It has made them
the most finely balanced ecosystems in the world
Only too easily
upset and destroyed
By that
other great ape
the chimpanzee's
closest relative
ourselves